[Music]
foreign
ography
[Music]
hello everyone this is Frankie Freitas
and welcome to holotalk for the week of
November 23rd
and Happy Thanksgiving this week in case
you happen to celebrate this holiday
if you are a student or educator
or someone who has an interest in making
Holograms as a hobby in your own home
studio or lab
I have got the most incredible news for
you on the show tonight
if this news doesn't Rock the holography
world then nothing will
you may also want to get a pencil and
Pad ready to take down some of the
information that you will learn about
tonight
I am holding in my hand a four by five
inch white light reflection hologram
which is the same style of or type of
hologram that you see on the walls of
countless hologram shops across the
country
it is crisp bright and Exhibits a great
amount of depth it's on egg for plate
now what makes this hologram special
is that it was not made with your
standard helium neon or other gas laser
which are lasers that have been the
standard for making holograms for over
30 years
what makes this hologram special is that
it was made using a standard off the
shelf and out of the box forty nine
dollar laser pointer
I'll repeat that this hologram was made
using a standard
off-the-shelf and out of the box
forty nine dollar laser pointer
the person who achieved this is Steve
Michael who is my guest tonight on
holotalk
Steve is going to tell us all the
details of using a laser pointer to make
Holograms so that you too can now get
involved with holography at a fraction
of the cost
of what is the most expensive part of
any holographic setup the laser
now before we begin the interview let me
give you some specific information on
this laser pointer that Steve was going
to tell us about during the interview
it is called the Rocket laser pointer
locket r-a-c-k-e-t
and can be found in the Edmond
scientific catalog
had been scientific is located in
Barrington New Jersey
and they can be reached at the following
telephone number
area code 609-573
area code 609
-573
-6250
they will send you a catalog if you call
and ask for one
ask for their latest Optics catalog
that's the one that I have that I found
the laser pointer in
the laser pointer or rocket laser is
it's known in the catalog its ordering
number is d
fifty four thousand zero zero six
that's d as in dog fifty four thousand
zero zero six and here are the specs
it is a class 3A laser pointer
power output is three to five milliwatts
at 635 nanometers
it's very close to the heaning at 633
nanometers
and it's also very close to the power of
many of the lasers that you find in the
classroom
it runs on two
LR44 alkaline batteries
and gets two and a half hours of
continuous operation from these
batteries
it also has an adjustable Focus lens and
a momentary on off switch
now as many many of you may remember
last year I ran a series of webcam
nights which I which you could log onto
the site and see a presentation in the
studio
I had a similar laser diode that I
demonstrated which was battery operated
that I had taken a diode out of the
housing and hooked it up to a Radio
Shack power supply to run the diode off
of standard household current
it may be possible to do this
with this laser pointer as well
saving you the money of having to
replace batteries all the time by just
plugging it into the wall
we'll have more on this later
as we continue to check in with Steve to
see what's new from time to time here on
Hollow talk
so why is this such a big deal well
it's certainly not a big deal if you're
working with a 20 watt argon laser
system but for kids with school projects
to
classroom and many hobbyists and
amateurs on tight budgets that really
want to get involved with photography
but could not do so
this is going to revolutionize this type
of holography
the most common emails I get here in the
studio can I make a hologram using a
laser pointer
in the past I've had to write back
saying that you can utilize your
hologram with the laser pointer but
because of the short coherence length of
laser diodes you could not make a
hologram until now
so let's move on to the interview with
Steve Michael and get the details he's
also going to have information up at his
site on laser pointer holography
and you can find a link to his site
right on the whole talk page now I won't
be coming back on after the interview so
I will thank you now for tuning in to
whole talk and hope that you continue to
come back each week for new and exciting
shows just like this one
here's the interview with Steve this is
Frankie Freitas for holotalk
let's get rolling and we'll start off
with your website which is an incredibly
well done site for amateur and hobbyist
holography especially with the guide and
everything that you have on there how
did you get started with the website uh
how long has it been up how much work
did you put into it could you let
listeners know a little bit about that
yeah I um
I wrote a couple papers in 1990 and 91
in the Journal of biological photography
and I wrote these papers so that
beginners in the field of biological
sciences might want to use a holography
for their recording medium and
both Bundt paper was called how to build
a holography system and the other one
was producing transmission and
reflection Holograms
so I decided right now I'm working on an
internet team
on the graphic arts team and I decided
I'd be a good chance for me to set up a
website and transfer that information so
the rest of the world
and I did that and I finished it in
August of 96. so it's been up a little
over two years
and it took me about 600 hours to
produce all the graphics because I had
to do those from scratches you know the
background graphic that you have on
there the laser pattern did you do that
yes is that the laser being sent through
like a piece of plexiglass or something
you've got it that's exactly right
that's a great shot technically it's a
great photograph oh thank you yes I
projected it on pill with just a piece
of white cardboard uh I set my camera up
so that it was in line with the
correction
the pattern was being projected in the
screen and just by I have a linear
translation stage of sitting on and just
by slightly moving the plastic I could
change the pattern it will
and and I had like 36 or 40 different
patterns that I photographed and then um
you know I started into Photoshop
instead of that version digital use yeah
usually that saturates the film and
those types of shots but that that's
just like right on the money
you have hologram Mart where you sell
some of your own editions too right yeah
what pieces do you have on there right
now
my original work
um was in the biological sciences so I
have a human skull and a
vaginal infection of the human brain and
these were actual real
specimens and then I did one of a lunar
lander
on the moon
in the landscape I created using clay
the guide itself is that something that
you wrote as the site progressed or did
you already have that written and you
just put it up that's almost like a
calligraphy manual yes I wrote that that
was the material I wrote in 1990 and 91.
and I just prescribed it over to HTML
what do you have in your lab is it in
your home yes it's in my basement
um what type of a table are you working
on
well it's really interesting I have a
glass table oh really yes um I've
progressed from a wooden tables to
sandbox to Marvel and now I have a five
by eight foot three quarter inch thick
glass table that's very interesting and
it's all
um gravity mounted the whole grains that
you sent me were produced on that table
right yes they were
it's very stable very rigid now here's
what everyone's waiting to hear I
received as I said at the beginning of
the show
two Holograms from Steve a single beam
reflection hologram
and a single beam laser transmission
hologram and these were really nice
Holograms
and Steve you did them with a laser
pointer that's correct
now my first question is is this just
off the shelf or did you do something to
the laser pointer no this is one just
off the shelf with batteries with
batteries three of them
no kidding yeah
and I bought the batteries you can buy a
Radio Shack yeah
so it wasn't like a laser that you took
the diode out of the pointer and hooked
the diode up to a power supply or
anything like that just out of the box
and you probably put tape or something
and make it stay on or did you have a
switch or something yeah it's one of
those momentary on switches and what I
did was it was clamped in one of these
Vice clamps so the actual laser was and
I had the button turned in such a way
that I could
put a pencil in another clamp and push
the different
place
now these things only last for like two
and a half hours the batteries yeah so
uh you kind of have to work fast and
you're set up and then you turn your
lights are off and then let her graph I
generally have
several extra boundaries
ready to go because when I actually make
my exposure I want fresh batteries in
there because I'm giving me the power I
needed yeah and how long do you leave
that laser on for I mean most of the gas
lasers like the helium neon they really
say how important it is to allow that
laser to reach thermal stability how
long would you say the laser pen was on
for before you would do your first
explosion
approximately five minutes no kidding
and what what power laser
this is a three to five milliwatt
operating do you know the wavelength yes
is that six four zero
um zero nanometers that's six four zero
nanometers these Holograms display an
incredible amount of depth yes I was
very interested in finding out uh
what the actual coherent length of these
were um I had done some research and
graphic specs when
on the more powerful dial later places
like the one two and five watt laces
in case you say that
the coherent length of these days are
around three to four millimeters
and plus the fact that they're randomly
polarized
and I was concerned about that and being
able to make a hologram
so I was a little discouraged that
dialed lasers would even work
exactly I mean
the emails that I get
always getting emails you probably get
them too can I do whole grain with a
laser pen and it's always been well you
may be able to do something like a
postage stamp or something like that but
you would never get any depth
well I decided to not believe what I
read because I would what I did was I
went to have the scientific notes their
rocket laser pointer okay the rocket
laser points from right out of the
catalog right out of the catalog they
have numerous other ones and the
wavelengths vary depending on which one
you get so in other words 670 nanometers
somewhere 650 675. with the same model
or okay different yes okay right and so
I got the one that was closest to 6328
for the um the film I was using because
I was using 80 75 oh okay
yeah
yeah so now this waster by the way costs
45 so right there we've brought the cost
down from like you know a five million
human neon from eight hundred dollars
down to like 45.
but um but I got to hear my laugh first
thing I checked was to see if it was
polarized and sure enough it was no
kidding
it just blew me away I didn't
think that was true well the next day I
went to Radio Shack and checked two of
their other models that they were two
models that they have there and they
were both polarized hmm
so I'm thinking I don't know whether all
laser pointers are now but at least
three models are yeah and then the next
thing was I set up a microphone what I
should have a microphone interferometer
to see if I could get Fringe patterns
yeah and I was amazing after that with
the path links being zero I got some
really nice high contrast ranges I bet
you thought you were really off and
running then
um and then I decided I wanted to find
out what the cool airplane length was so
I started to move one of the mirrors
and I got it all the way out to 10
inches oh my goodness and I was still
getting Fringe patterns very sharp
as you can see that hologram I sent you
is probably three centimeters deep
yeah easy easy
it looks just like you shot it with a
helium neon laser in fact I would go out
on the limb and say it's better than a
lot of the classroom laser uh Holograms
that I've seen as far as brightness
and depth
well I put the object of course if I
could to the films or the past
differences were minimal yeah
um the other problem though with the
diode laser is that it doesn't have a
circular beam profile oh I see yeah it's
rectangular at least the one I have
and I found that by the way this
particular dialogue laser pointer has a
lands in front of the diode so you can
focus it to a sharp Point well you know
out to 100 feet and if you actually do
Focus that to Infinity you get to a
sharp point from the laser pointer all
the way out to that distance
hmm well what I had to do was
I had to adjust that lens such a way
behind my microscope objective which was
going to diverge the beams cover the
whole 4x5 plate
in such a way that I got you know
forward here across the plate and that
was a little difficult I mean I even
used the pinhole to try to clean it up
some yeah but trying to put you know it
was like trying to put a rectangle
through a circle yeah
that did your exposure time run on these
shots
it was
one minute for the transmission
and two minutes for the reflection
hmm
that's pretty short yeah
I'm trying to think
it's been a while since I've had a three
or five millilitini but I'm trying to
think of what the single being exposure
times would be on the 80 75 HD with
tahini
well um I went and set up my five
milliwatts which my power meter was
saying was operated about 6.2 milliwatts
yeah my social time's around two seconds
single B
that's interesting why do you think the
difference here it's not that much
difference in the power
could be the profile being spread out
further that way I see it certainly
didn't look as bright because I did take
a power meter reading on the dial Laser
when I had new batteries and I was
getting 3.3 now there's about that's
about a three milliwatt difference yeah
um
which is half of what you were seeing
with tahini but yet more than twice the
time
on the exposure
right
um in any case it's a wonderful job oh
thank you a beautiful hologram I mean
that laser transmission hologram is is
gorgeous and the reflection hologram it
seems the box was handed to me I opened
the box up and uh with the lamp that I
have on my desk I saw the image right
away
I did try a tubing setup
and that was very difficult in fact I
wasn't successful
getting the
plate covered
uniformly and also being able to
uniformly cover the object it's again a
function of that lens in front
to diode plus having to split the Bean
cut your power in hand in each of them
and so that's that's a bit difficult but
for the student that wants to do a
single Beam for a science project we
work today well Steve I'm going to go
out and win
and I'm going to say that probably what
you've just done
could very well revolutionize holography
not only in this country but around the
world
that's interesting you mean in terms of
in terms of making it available to more
people who will get involved with it and
continue to grow in their interest and
put in studios and their own places to
do Holograms well that's what I was
hoping for if this was successful which
it was brings cost way down and you
don't have to have a big table like mine
either and you know how many people want
to do Holograms using a laser pointer
right you know I mean you see the emails
I see them all the time imagine now
that you can write back to those people
and tell them yes you can do a hologram
with a laser pointer yes it's a great
feeling yeah it's incredible well I want
to congratulate you Steve
it's not too often that we get somebody
on the show that has done what you've
done
I admire you because you didn't listen
to what other people were telling you
and you just went ahead and did it
anyway which I really like
I want to thank you for coming on and I
want to tell the listeners that you can
go to the 3D imagery.com and I'll have a
link for that for the www first
Okay so we've got
www.3d
imagery.com you'll see a link for it
right on the whole talk page you can
click on that link and go over to the
site let me ask you this before we close
it out do you think you're going to put
anything on your website about your
experiment and results most definitely
most definitely yeah that will happen in
the next couple months and one other
thing we have talked to you about
finding a cheaper film too oh okay yes
that's right yes you're working with the
tech yeah
um that didn't turn out and I did
several exposures in different
um angles between
the being and that's pretty restrictive
I mean if you try to get down to 10
degree difference and keep your spatial
frequency down then you you're not
you're not very practical anymore
um
I did call Kodak today and found out
that Kodak still produces the fo253
holographic film and that's in sheet 4x5
sheets comes 25 in a box
for 61.55
so we're looking at less expense there
too yeah
and in smaller quantities then you have
to buy a lot of the other hymns as well
right and if you call Kodak that um
800-242-2424 they'll send out the specs
of that film well Steve thank you very
much uh hang on the line for a minute
after I close this out I'm going to pick
up the phone okay thank you